I think if you slurp or cough during the
meditation it's like it's like
somebody's asleep and they're they're
being sustained by the sleep and
you you like bang on their shoulder you
know try really hard not
to again if it starts to come to your
nose just open your mouth and breathe
through your mouth and let it drip it
doesn't hurt anything okay one good
slurp it's like shaking somebody away
somebody's somebody deep asleep and they
were really tired and then you
like so try try really
hard watch your breath please
e e
then go to the Garden
Room
e
e e
you watch the sky
outside e
and look down and see the
mountains separated from you by the
valley covered with
light e
come back into the Cen room
and ask your teacher to please
come sit with
you and they put their hands on your
hands
Focus very specifically on the touch of
their head so you don't even see them
really you're you have some awareness
that they're there
but the object of the meditation is the
touch of their hand on your
hand and be contented with that touch
don't think you need to go anywhere
else you're just
alone
silent in a
room with your
teacher you're just touching your hand
and that's
all no place else to go nothing else to
do e
if you lose the object you think of
something
else the mind gets
sleepy try to cut through
more try to
raise the Luminous golden quality try
to
enjoy the touch
more be satisfied content be willing to
study
feel a sense
ofate that you're not bombarding with
sof locked down you're just there quiet
in a room
and feed of that relief feel the sense
of sustaining that it gives you
e e
now try to observe your
sh try to watch your watchfulness
isolate that state of mind
mind and watch how it steps
in when the mind wanders or gets
dull observe your own capacity for
observation e
and watch the part of your mind that
pulls your mind back
Timba the capacitate the mind to pull
the Mind back to the object in
meditation e
again try to connect with your
n with a feeling of relief almost or
contentment that you
can be still and stay still and
quiet it's
now e
and slowly come back to this s
slowly open your
eyes so we were at
uh we were talking about a description
of level
9 and it said
uh it's not in your chart okay uh it
says
D sh J okay d
so we talked
about
means that State of Mind was still in
the desire room okay meaning
what if you
had sustained that state of mind for a
long time in this life you would be
reborn into a desire
room and then it
was it was on a single object
eag and it was it was good it was Auto
autopilot uh no agitation no dullness
and lots of more okay by the way I mean
when you get
home try
to try to remember what your sh feels
like what does it feel like to watch
your mind sometimes look for your
watchfulness during meditation look for
your watchfulness and see how it's doing
and then sometimes watch your mind bring
your mind back look at your recollection
Your Capacity to bring the Mind back and
then sometimes I think most import maybe
the most important thing of all check in
on
your you know see if you
can sorry that speaker is not working is
it no right speaker Di
better it's
bad check in on your
n i I really can't overemphasize
the the the power of a feeling of
contentment with the situation you know
like that's enough for me I would like
to just be here with you okay you had
lar in the car with your high school
boyfriend from 12: to
4:30 okay and then your mom came out and
knocked on the
window you know and uh just time passed
and I remember that one time the lady
was her father but
anyway uh you know banging on the window
and uh it's that kind of feeling like I
don't have any place else to go you know
so try really hard to bring up that
sense of
contentment a sign of it would be
uh a sign that you haven't is that in
your normal life you're able to sit in a
chair quietly focus and not get on your
computer and not use your cell phone and
not check your email you know if if
otherwise you really do have a problem I
think all these modern devices and every
generation has had it modern devices
ever since papyruses and stuff
uh they distract you you know and they
keep your mind busy so be very
careful uh Duna right one of the
conditions for meditation don't get
overly busy or overly stimulated
television is really bad newspapers are
really bad I think email is a step
up uh on the distraction you know it
just I'm not sure you can meditate well
and do email in the same day I don't
know
but I know everybody would die if you
didn't do emails
so uh what you might do is set a time a
day that you do your email you know like
I just do it once today you don't need
to be up to date up to the moment you
know prob whatever people emailed you
about you can know about
tomorrow you know it's not going to
matter that much and we get more and
more addicted the more you use it you
know I have to have it on almost
constantly now and I'm checking every
few minutes to see if someone's written
me a new email about the talking
Singapore in
June you know what I mean and it's okay
tomorrow would be okay to to read about
it you know so maybe pick a time of day
that I nowadays I try to do my emails in
the afternoon I pick a time when my mind
is pretty much useless for anything good
and then I do my emails doing that
pretty it doesn't require my fresh
morning state of mind and uh it will
disturb my sleep most of the emails I
get would disturb my sleep so uh you
know afternoon is a good your low time
is a good time to do your emails uh
but try
to just observe your life do you ever
just go for a walk or do you ever just
sit in the room quietly by yourself and
without without doing nothing but
without doing anything you
see can you just
relax and be with yourself for 10
minutes or 15
minutes and if you cannot I don't think
you can meditate
okay all
[Music]
right so I'm I'm going to the actual
text now I haven't done this yet as far
as the meditation side of things um I've
been working against a poster but at
this point the poster gets a little
sparse okay uh like they're just naming
the states of nine plus States and they
don't explain them so what I'd like to
do is to go to the original text by
PAB and this happens to be what he's
talking about just before he gets to The
Emptiness part that you started with
this week okay right so he's bridging
between
n level 9 plus and all the emptiness
stuff we've been talking about that's
where he is in the text okay
Dan so you have to get used to the word
sh okay you have to get used to the idea
shamata and Viana so now we're on a
whole very important subject okay
there's
a very high
state of meditation called sham sham
sham means peace right sham means
peace calm comes from that word and
ultimately quiet comes from that word
because they both come from krisham
which came into Latin and other
langu romanic languages as
Asam as
in okay changes to uh so calm or quiet
come from all they all come from sham so
sham means quiet sh means a state of
that like shin or
shamata different spellings but they
mean the same thing shamata is a state
of Peace okay the and the Tibetans
translated it that way they called it sh
she means peace and N means a state of
so they translated shamata very nicely
shama and t uh
sh
uh sh means after he died okay so we're
not going to say
sh okay it's a sh
sh sh means sham
okay that's sort of nine plus okay nine
nine
itself is called sh J tumba J tumba
means uh
approximate
approximation approximation it's an
approximation of shamata okay that's a
May right approximation means not quite
the real thing okay so Shin J tumba is
sort of an
insult okay level n is called
Shin level N9 is
called Almost shamata okay a good
approximation of shamata it means it
ain't okay it's not shamata yet it's not
SH now I'm going to pick up the text
from there okay I'm going to pick up the
text from there and we'll go with the
text below because the poster I don't
know I think when they got towards the
end of the poster they were in a rush or
something I don't know okay so here we
go
Goa level n is accomplished
through the power right how many Powers
six through the power
of
complete familiarity familiarity okay
complete
familiarity now he's going to summarize
the nine stages
okay and uh he's not going to tell you
sorry he's going to summarize the nine
levels without telling he's going to
give
three uh steps to a metaphor he does not
uh exactly correlate them to nine levels
he doesn't say you know the first step
feels like the first three or something
like he just says over the course of the
nine levels you will feel it'll feel
like three different feelings going on
okay number one
uh during the first third of the chart
during the first third of the poster you
feel like you're just getting to
know the problems in your own mind okay
D what's dullness what's
agitation what's a loss
of what's subtle
dullness what's subtle agitation so the
the feel
during the first third of
the poster is that you feel like you're
just getting to know your own head you
just getting to know your own mind
number
two during the second part of your
career up the up the path of this poster
you will feel
like
those meditation problems are giving you
a break sometimes like they're letting
you take a little bit of rest sometimes
like they stop harassing you
temporarily on and off they stop
harassing you okay like you feel like
relief you know like oh you know
dullness agitation thinking about lunch
subtle
dullness getting Spacey subtle agitation
almost thinking about lunch all these
things are they're like cutting me some
slack sometimes that's the second
feeling third
feeling then in the third in the in the
final stages of this path this poster
you feel like they are they're getting
fatigued okay your agitation is is
Tucker out your agitation is getting
tired of agitating you okay and it feels
nice you know like
they're losing their strength to bug
you you've been working on them and they
they feel exhausted instead of you feel
exhausted right
okay so he's going to give the answer to
the homework question I posed to you
which
was what what is it that separates each
successive step from the previous stage
okay what is it that separates level two
from level one why did they make a level
there why did they feel it was necessary
to say there's another level there there
must be some difference between the new
state and the previous state okay so
here's you can check this with what you
thought okay here we
go what separates the second level from
the first
is how long you can continue to stay on
the
object the relative duration on the
object is what separates level two from
level one so we're going to keep
separating right now we going to know
now we want to know what separates level
three from level two
okay uh what separates the third
level from the second level is the
duration of the
distraction meaning it's getting
shorter okay three is distinguished from
Two by The shortening of the
destruction less distraction at three
[Music]
twoing the difference between three and
four by the way this is why they came
out with nine states okay this is why
there's nine levels cuz there are nine
differences okay
uh number four is distinguished from
number three in that it is no longer
possible to lose the other okay
completely she
level four is distinguished from Level
sorry sorry level five is distinguish
from level four and that it's no long in
that you no longer get obvious dullness
gross
dullness number six six is distinguished
from number
five in that you no
longer need to worry much okay about
whether you're going to get subtle
dness that's a
m number six is also distinguished from
number number five in that although it's
still possible to get subtle agitation
it will be much shorter in duration then
at
five why are we going through all this I
mean I had people came up to me
and made me aware that this whole class
is pretty
technical
uh in about six months you're going to
want to know did I make it to six or am
I still at five you know and and this
very
helpful like in in in grade school and
high school you know what class you're
in you know like if you're a freshman
you can't ask a sophomore girl out it's
not going to work okay it doesn't matter
how cool you are it's not going to work
out you know you don't even try right
it's it's not possible but there's this
Comfort to know you where you are if if
from the age of six to the age of 18
they said you're in
school but we don't know what class you
know like we don't know if you're eighth
grader or you got to know if you're a
freshman or a sophomore cuz then you
know who you can ask out right
so it's it's somehow nice to know what
it's very comforting to know what level
you're on because inner things are very
difficult to
quantify you know we went to British Air
we had a meeting with the top 12 people
who were interested in having a DCI
training and one guy just you know he
was like wait you know I like this whole
idea this diamond color thing is very
good uh but metrics metrics metrics you
know I'm like I'm like whisper and
yingbo and Mercedes know what's metrics
mean you know and uh he's like how are
we going to measure the effect of your
programs on our people 40,000 people how
are you going to measure the effects of
this
worldview on people you know so it's
this it's very difficult to quantify
your
inl uh but if someone comes along and
gives you some
guidelines uh it's so
comforting okay it's really really uh
feels good even if you're at level two
or level three at least you know how far
you have to go it's very frustrating if
if you've been meditating for 3 years
like in karate they give you different
color belts right and it means a lot you
know like okay I got my green belt you
know I got my blue belt I never got past
yellow okay uh that's another story but
uh at least you know where you are and
you feel some kind of comfort to know
where you are so it's better to know
that your meditation is at level two
than to not know where you are okay so
that's why we're doing this exercise
especially this question of what
distinguishes each preceding one from
the sorry proceeding one from the
preceding one okay uh so I think we're
between six and
seven I think we just had that
[Music]
oh okay
uh whether or not there's any great
concern that you might completely fall
into subtle dullness or agitation so the
main thing is he's added agitation okay
cuz already we didn't have much danger
of subtle dullness right but he threw it
into the difference between six and
seven also but he also added that verb
about losing yourself sh okay not any no
longer any great need to be cautious
about whether you will lose yourself in
subtle dullness or
agitation by the way there's
traditionally there's a little trouble
distinguish six and seven as you can
feel right and there's more information
coming number eight is distinguished
from number
seven in the question of is it even any
longer
possible uh that you could have any form
of dullness or
agitation there is no longer any
dullness or
agitation in eight and that's what
distinguishes it from
seven so you would wonder then what's
going to distinguish nine from8 if you
if you already have no
possibility of dullness or agitation
then what distinguishes nine from
eight number nine is distinguish from
number eight in that you no longer have
to make any conscious effort to stay
there okay it's effortless it's
completely effortless you still have no
dullness and you still have no agitation
but now it's
effortless now he clarifies the
difference between seven and six cuz he
also felt uncomfortable I think with it
he goes back to the difference between
what why is seven better than six okay
he says dup at the seven
uh at the seventh level uh you might all
you have to do is just kind
of touch on your dullness and agitation
and they're gone you don't have to worry
that you will be lost in them or that
you will swim in them or okay so it's a
difference like you might get
agitation or dullness but you won't like
wallow in it short means wallow okay
you're not going to wallowing them
there'll be a something will come up and
you'll just block it right away okay but
there's no danger that you're going to
be hopelessly wallowing
okay uh and then he gives the example
that we talked about
before if you're boxing with somebody
okay if you're boxing with
somebody if you're boxing with somebody
and it's in the late rounds and they
have lost most of their strength their
strength has dwindled
okay you then you don't have to be like
totally on your guard all the time okay
like the guy's ability to punch he might
get a punch in but it's going to be
weak it's not going to have any punch
behind it so so you don't have to be
like protecting your head as actively as
you did before so at level seven you
don't have to protect your head as
against dullness and agitation as
actively as you did at earlier
okay you
can you can block him easily okay like
he throws a punch and you just kind of
SWAT at it and it's enough because
there's no power behind
it so in after that
discussion
uho till six okay um after that
uh P took a break for the day right the
whole topic that we've covered so far
about meditation he did in a single day
okay like no those sessions were 12 18
hours and people in Tibet were used to
that and they would walk around and hand
out uh Tibetan
tea which is sort of like
jol uh
okay like a very strong C okay all right
uh programmers use like jol right okay
uh I had it
once that's a main gu okay
very famous
okay the
king of
the geese okay
Hansa which came into guns which became
Lans and means Goose The End dropped off
in English Okay uh so the Hansa flies at
the what do you call
at the head of the other geese the head
Goose flies at the leads if you've ever
seen a flock of that's very beautiful
you know I don't know who picks the head
one or you know but it seems like a
heavy responsibility you know he's got
to get to Antartica you know and and so
the head gr uh needs two wings okay two
powerful Wings what are they
okay they are uh theep of reality and
Ultimate Reality the reality we live in
which is called it's called deceptive
because it fools you
why
ding okay ding that's deceptive reality
it looks as though it's coming from the
pen it looks as though the pen is in the
pen it looks as though the power to cure
your headache is in the
ASP and therefore all those things which
work that way or seem to work that way
but obviously don't work if you question
it for 10
seconds okay cars break down planes fall
down aspirins don't
work they got you fooled man they really
got you you know you go to wall was it
Walgreens and you pay full price for the
Bott of aspin you come home and half of
them don't work and no and nobody ever
goes back to ask for their money back or
half their money back it's amazing they
got you they you you're used to it I
think you'd even feel uncomfortable if
all the Asin weren or if your car never
broke down or if your boyfriend was just
totally sweet and devoted and
pure
permanently you know I don't know if you
feel comfortable with it but uh
anyway so that reality is called
deceptive reality the world of deceptive
reality K and then the other so a
knowledge of a knowledge of deceptive
reality is One Wing okay and then a
knowledge of Ultimate Reality is another
Wing it's one thing to convince people
that Aspen don't
work it's another thing to tell them how
to get them to work okay and my llama my
dear
sweet matchless
way
llama uh always always tells me you know
you can disprove that aspirin work but
you you you darn well better not leave
people there know don't leave them
doubting their whole world you know
like teach that in the first half of the
lecture and then don't have a break and
then teach them how to make the ASP work
you can't
just leave somebody with your aspin
didn't work and you never noticed it and
good luck you know like that you can't
do that that okay you have you have to
go on to how to get the aspin to work
all the time so anyway you
need to point out that things are not
what they seem to they don't work like
people think and then you have to give
them the other side which is Ultimate
you know the explanation of ultimate
real and that the goose can only need
the other geese you can only teach other
people if you have both wings okay if
you can
explain why the thing doesn't work
really and then how to get it to work
really okay which is which is helping
other people with their headaches okay
all
right the head Goose flies then at the
at the head of the other
beings and the wind uh the power of the
wind of virtue
propelled by
the powerful Wing what do you call
propulsive
propulsion okay the propulsion power of
their virtue okay jet fuel
GA they reached
the this is a hard thing in English how
to say
it uh crossing a dangerous ocean to
another place of sanctuary
is considered a metaphor for completion
in tibetan scripture and what comes in
my mind when I hear it is could you make
a non-stop flight from LA to Tokyo you
see and then often the ocean is compared
to
the some qualities of an enlightened
being so crossing the ocean flying
non-stop LA to Tokyo in 1940 or 19 you
know when it was barely possible
is often used as a metaphor in scripture
for for acquiring all the qualities of
an enlightened being you know the the
ocean is the qualities of enlightened
being to cross it and hit Tokyo non-stop
is a metaphor for gaining all those
qualities so the the the head Goose can
lead the other geese from LA to Tokyo
and cross over meaning acquire all the
qual of enlightened being if they can
grasp how the pen
is why the pen appears to come from its
own side or how the
pen how the pen really does come through
the seeds right and then the
emptiness of what it seemed to be before
okay with those two great
ideas oh things are a white screen and
what I see is coming from my seats with
those two ideas you can fly to
enlightenment and you can lead others
there that's cool that was
chandi Master
chandi then he
clarifies the two
Wings can be
called
and okay so b means as you know
[Music]
from the wish for enlightenment is to
strive or to want to get enlightened uh
for the sake of everybody for for
everyone to save the world you want to
get Enlighten to save the world so they
say this ultimate love has two focuses
one save the world two
become an enlightened being so you can
do it okay so ultimate love has two
focuses that love is called the
deceptive wish for enlightenment okay
because it's still dealing in deceptive
reality and then there's an ultimate
form of that wish which is the direct
perception emptiness okay
so
Pon is glossing the deceptive in the
verse by chti and saying One Wing is the
wish to save all beings and the other
Wing is the understanding of emptiness
that would allow that okay all
right you can also explain it as uh the
collection of virtue and Merit but
that's a merit and wisdom okay but
that's another
story uh
uh then this was you know this text is a
record of a teaching
given over 24 days by Pon so then he
says hok went on to explain why we
needed
to get good teachings on emptiness and
meditation or we wouldn't be able to do
it very well okay so so you you'll never
be able to understand emptiness very
well and you won't be able to meditate
very well unless you get good clear
teachings on it okay so he he talked
about that for a
while then he talked about uh lundo okay
lundo which means the preliminary
practices which is the subject of a
great of a huge section of this text and
we'll start it in April okay we'll go
back to the beginning of the text and uh
there'll be a the best explanation in
the lineage of the
Dias of of the preliminary practices
okay very very beautiful very very very
beautiful okay and then we'll go back
we'll start at the
beginning uh sh but anyway on the 22nd
day he reviewed that a bit okay and
then he reviewed the outline of the
topics he had taught so far
and
then then he talked about the five or we
can say the six conditions that you need
to prepare to meditate okay which
were what is
that uh get a good place to medic
place don't want too many things
choke enjoy the things you do
have
uh try to reduce your stimulation over
stimulation then the most important
one uh s number
Doctor uh don't hurt other people be
kind to other people collect Good Karma
because that Karma creates the blitz so
I hope you had that class this morning
and last night you had those two classes
one was about the karma you need the new
Good Karma one was about the old Bad
Karma you have to get rid of to reduce
the blips from happening in the first
place then you don't have to deal with
them with the antidotes it's a blip that
never
blipped okay all right that's what we
really want this number five is the best
and then it was
what what was this
didn't we do
oh get rid of random thoughts like you
know sex on the Internet or uh I got to
get to Dunkin Donut in the next 15
minutes like okay all right this kind of
random desire thought like that okay
those were the six but he said he said
do said five or six or what are the five
leg leg La easy to find what you need
food food and
Etc what we're hoping to supply to the
three Retreats without a break par okay
we're hoping uninterrupted supply of
healthy food and propane
Etc
okay you should see the estimates anyway
that's my problem right uh so anyway
honestly acquired properly acquired
without harm to other beings uh supplies
and then uh
n uh a nice a pure place which has been
blessed by holy being
S no dangerous
animals uh not too cold not too
hot
uh uh talk sble what was
that uh good
friends good and
then you should have your poster when
you go in the
retreat you you should have your
instructions you should have your
instructions all set the three retrea
went in with seven years of of
explanation of the practice they
doing thousands of hours of teaching on
on the on the practice they're supposed
to be doing okay so that's what he meant
when he said five or six preliminaries
or stuff that you need to
start then if you will recall says we
spoke about the five problems and eight
eight Corrections for them
okay and then you will recall that by
applying the eight antidotes to the five
problems you would pass through nine
stages of nine levels of
meditation
[Music]
uh he went through he reviewed the six
powers do you want to do that you want
to go through that okay we'll just go
quickly through the six
parts you get to the first level of
meditation by the Imp
of learning the instructions from your
teacher you get to the second level of
meditation by going home and considering
those
instructions reviewing them
right will your meditation poster
collect dust in the next six months
that's why I'm giving you a tube so at
least it's
protected okay you get your tubes
tomorrow I think or something start I'm
not sure they're
coming
uh third level and fourth level are
attained to
the mature Power Of Your Capacity to
bring your mind back to the object
[Music]
the fifth and sixth levels are
characterized by the full maturation or
development of your capacity to catch
yourself going off the object
sh seventh level and eighth level are
achieved to the power he said effort but
we said extra effort or the last effort
or that
last that final effort it takes to wipe
out even subtle dullness and subtle
agitation okay going the extra what do
they say in English you can't tell me
going the extra mile yeah like you don't
quit when it's almost perfect you you do
the little last part you need to like a
paint job in a house and then you like
come back on the third day and you you
do the touchup work
uh and then level 9 is attained through
the power of becoming completely
familiar with meditation and it becomes
automatic goes into
automatic
okay he's gonna review the four state of
mind
you kind of said how it sort of how it
feels as you go through the
N during the first two
levels you you kind of have to really
gear gear up your mind you have to work
really hard to get started getting
started takes a lot of
concentration you have to really sit
down and collect your thumbs
and then you can meditate but it it
takes some great effort to pull your
mind out of your daily schedule and get
it into meditation
okay the
inter the intervening fire which means 3
4 5 6 and 7 okay levels 3 4 5 6 and
seven
Chupa the meditation is Flowing but
somebody keeps
coughing I
mean top tapping you on the shoulder
okay okay dullness or agitation keeps
tapping you on the shoulder you you got
to float and then it gets interrupted
which is
extremely bad for the sustaining thing
the food thing uh as we said to some
someone to cough during a deep
meditation session or someone to shake
you away after two hours of sleep
and if you have trouble going back to
sleep they're very similar as far as the
harm done to
your the sustaining of your body and
your mind
okay
sorry at the eighth level you're able to
continue in your meditation without
interruption but it takes some effort it
still takes a tiny amount of
effort dup dup and at the ninth level
finally it's spontaneous it's effortless
and spontaneous
okay so we now have
four you got you got everything right
you got nine levels you got six cars you
got four states of mind you got five
problems you got eight out of those
okay this is very cute he poses us a
question do do you imagine right we said
it's only the five intervening levels
that are interrupted by dullness and
agitation right they were called the
State of Mind where you feel you are
being interrupted by dullness and
agitation right he says do you imagine
that your first two levels aren't
interrupted by dullness and editation
like duh you know you think you think
you're not getting tapped on the
shoulder big time in the first level and
the second level what did you think
you know so then his student says to
babon say well well then why didn't they
they why didn't they call the first two
levels you know interrupted he said what
[Laughter]
interrupted Jer me jerine mea means they
don't deserve the name of
interrup cuz there's no flow
nothing to
interrupt okay it's cute okay it's kind
of cute it's not
cute uh and the first two levels are
also places where you you really have to
tighten down with your
awareness uh you know your alarm state
of mind and your capacity to bring the
Mind
back so the the the intervening five
steps 3 to seven was it three four five
six seven yeah you want to look at this
is cool okay you want to know you're
real Buddhist scholar you have to count
things like on your joints and on your
fingers okay then they know you're
really cool like his Holiness will go
one 2 3 four five okay
anyway in the intervening five levels
your capacity
for real concentration is is gradually
increasing uh and they are and it is
continually attacked by those by
dullness and agitation okay attack is
what you call it the attack is
continuous the attack on your meditation
is continuous so we call it flow with
Interruption somebody taing on your
shoulder level number eight is called
the State of Mind where you feel like
you are flowing without interruption
because at the beginning of a meditation
session if you assert just minimal
effort then that's all you need to have
a full session of perfect
meditation so at level eight still a
little bit of effort to get in but then
it's automatic then it's on
automatic uh and you're no longer
harassed you're no longer interrupted at
all at level 9
level N9 is distinguished from eight in
that you don't even have to make that
initial effort okay you you come down
into meditation I like to say you know
like you're you cross your legs and then
you get your hands like this and then
you do your chin mudra and then you go
like this and when the wrists hit the
knees you're in and no effort you just
actually the feeling there I would add
another feeling which
is uh you feel like you're just picking
up where you left off the last session a
few hours before or day before you feel
like you just came back to where you
were the day
before it's as if you didn't do anything
between the two sessions yeah you you
wris hit your knees and you're back in
the session you were in
yesterday okay
okay this is where I wanted to get today
we have about 10 minutes
here so what how do you get to real
shamata from Level n that's what we're
talking about now
okay and this gets into some very very
deep interesting questions I thought
that Allison West might like this part
uh CU it talks about he brings in Prana
he brings in the subtle movements of
Prana at these levels so it's very
beautiful
okay once you have achieved level nine
sh
to uh you can conduct a meditation
session without even subtle forms of
dullness and
agitation and
effortlessly for a long duration of time
hours okay sometimes they say four hours
I'm not going to say that okay I hate it
when people come up to me and say G I'm
up to 3 minutes and 57 seconds you know
and I'm like forget it you know if you
have 10 minutes of good meditation
that's okay okay
[Music]
anyway even though you may get to that
point it is only an approximation of sh
and it ain't the real thing it's not the
real thing yeah okay it's only close but
no okay
uh how' you translate that right just
kid she has a hard
job uh you know now this is of high
interest to all of us right and and this
is where we're going uh the rest of the
retreat uh so how do I go from nine to
the F flying you know how can I go from
nine to shamata because that's is what
we all want to know right
so here we're starting that question now
and we won't have much time but we'll
continue uh
tomorrow you must go back and just keep
doing level 9 over and over again
getting to level 9 over and over again
until you get really good at it okay so
you have to get good at reaching level n
you know you have to get good at being
at level n okay keep going back keep
meditating keep going up to level 9 get
used to what it's like to be at love and
life over and over
okay and you will have a thing that we
call Shin okay you will get a thing that
we call
Shin let me look at
something for
uh I was kind of hoping that there was
some well-known
sense but I don't think there
is
ver okay there
isn't here it
is oh here it is PRI okay PR anyway
that's
the you must go beyond level 9 and try
to add a new
component which is the exceptional
pleasure of mental and physical
proficiency
okay shinjang say shinjang
a
trick
uh shinjang I don't know it's
been shindu janga means uh extremely
well
trained but what it refers to is a
physical and and mental sensation
of of high pleasure
okay in meditation from the meditation
okay so it's a your body feels like
you're floating on air and your mind
feels like
it's you
know I don't know it's in your kiss with
your first boyfriend you know what I
mean it's like your mind is high and
your body feels like it's floating okay
that's shinan there's a mental version
and there's a physical version okay but
if you want to get from level 9 on you
have to find shinan okay you have to
reach shinan which is not an unpleasant
exercise okay okay you'd like to get to
a point where your body in meditation
feels like it's floating on the air and
your mind feels this deep sense of
Joy there are two kinds of shin Jang
what do you want to call Shin Jang some
people you could say fluency or I don't
know let's just call it Shin Jang okay
it's like I'd rather have you have a new
word for it okay let's just call it
shinjang so you know what shinjang mean
shinjang means physically and mentally
high from your meditation okay and you
need it if you want to get to 9 plus if
you want to go to shamata from nine you
got to have Shin okay uh NE there are
two forms of shinjang SE
shinjang mental and physical okay now
this is
interesting fluency in meditation and
the body becoming totally used to
meditation of those
two uh the the mental fluency comes
first and then later the physical
fluency comes Shin Jang from the point
of view of expertise or fluency or
Mastery the mental one comes first
but but with regard to the two Pleasures
the physical one comes
first okay so if I ask
you of mental or physical
shinjang shinjang meaning where you're
absolutely a master of meditation do you
get the physical Mastery first first or
do you get the mental Mastery first and
the answer is you get the mental Mastery
first but if I ask you do you feel a
bodily sensation of high pleasure or do
you feel a mental sensation of high
pleasure first it's the bodily one that
comes first okay that's a
distinction uh
now he's going to get into a
subject of what's happening to your
Prana in a state of shin that makes the
Bliss come on Bly and mental okay he's
going to start
describing what H what's happening to
your
Prana that makes these two kinds of
Mastery and these two kinds of high
pleasure come on okay and that's why
that's one of the reasons why in this
Retreat and with all of our students in
this lineage we're encouraging people to
do yoga or something
similar
because when you get to this stage if
you've been working on your Prana if
you've been working on your channels if
you've been doing your yoga especially
niguma or something
similar then then this part will come on
much easier okay because you're used to
working with your channels and you're
used to working with your PR so we're
trying to prepare you now wherever you
are level one level two level three that
at level 9 you will already know your
inner body and you will be in a position
to use The Prana to use the chi
uh to go from 9 to 9 plus because to get
bodily shinjang and to get mental
shinjang you're going to have to do some
things with the winds okay to get that
feeling of high
pleasure uh which is required to see
emptiness you see the physical and
mental feeling of high pleasure and the
Mastery it it implies is necessary to
get the
Sham okay from Sam from Simple Sam
from a state of deep meditation to a
state of meditation which can perceive
emptiness you between there what
separates
them is moving your winds in a proper in
a certain way and getting to certain
High states of pleasure physical and
mental pleasure in your meditation okay
which is kind of a fun you
know subject okay okay so we'll start
that uh tomorrow we'll start shinjang
tomorrow okay